<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Luis Garcia</title>
    <description>This is the personal website of Luis Garcia. Here you can read both technical and non-technical blogs, look at some projects, and get a little more insight about what makes him tick.</description>
    <link>/</link>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Mar 2020 17:32:46 -0400</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 08 Mar 2020 17:32:46 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.8.5</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Image Hosting with AWS</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;new-website-new-problems&quot;&gt;New Website, New Problems&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m hosting this latest version of my website using Jekyll in combination with Github Pages. If you want to know more about that process you can read my post on that &lt;a href=&quot;https://luisgarcia.me/blog/non-technical/NewBlogWhoThis&quot;&gt;here.&lt;/a&gt; Its been great! I’ve still not been contributing as much as I’d like, but I am contributing more! Along with new content, I’m also able to create and deploy site design changes with just as much speed. One of those changes is how I’m hosting the images in the background at the top of the page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Originally, I only used one background image for my website, the one with four couches and a girl. I wanted was to be able to show off more of my photos, so I added the images and a little javascript to randomize when they appeared. Job well done right? Well, there are a couple problems. First, I use a reasonably decent (read: nice for 2015) camera and its images can be quite large. For that matter, media files in general, depending on quality and compression, can be quite large. Since I’m using Github to host my website, I may &lt;a href=&quot;https://help.github.com/en/github/managing-large-files/what-is-my-disk-quota&quot;&gt;run into their size restrictions&lt;/a&gt; if I store too many photos. Second, Github is generally used to store code repositories. Using it as a website hosting platform is a nice feature but those two pieces of functionality don’t alway agree on how to do things. Github and other repositories are not &lt;em&gt;generally&lt;/em&gt; the ideal place to host images. Third, every deployment with an image change can take a long time to upload to the Github server.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For my initial implementation, I was lucky enough to have the option to host my images in Github, but that needed to change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;my-first-idea&quot;&gt;My First Idea&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AWS costs money, and I didn’t want to pay. I wanted my cake and to eat it to, that is, I wanted my images to be hosted somewhere but I wanted to have strong control over those images and my IP (intellectual property). I probably could have used Imgur, Flickr, or maybe even Instagram as free public solutions to host my images. I didn’t like the inherent public nature of image hosting on the platform. For my pictures with my friends, sure they’re great. Vacation pictures, awesome! For storing my amateur photography? No way. &lt;img src=&quot;https://i.giphy.com/media/fceh5CXz9mjHa/200.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Protected GIF&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tried using a private or even public album with Google Photos, but it seems Google has gotten wise and discourages direct links to photos. It seems like some companies may have come up with ways to get around this, but most of those seemed like hack-y solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, my desire to control my images was more powerful than my desire for free solutions, but AWS S3 bucket hosting, in this case, was cheap enough for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;enter-aws&quot;&gt;Enter AWS&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m sure there are a ton of ways to configure AWS resources, store your images, and grant access to them. However, I think this method is probably the simplest and most straightforward. I chose to upload my photos to a certain directory in an S3 bucket and grant public read access to that bucket.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Breaking this down a bit, these are the steps that I needed to host images from AWS and use them on this site.
    1. Login and Create an S3 Bucket
    2. Configure the S3 Bucket
    3. Upload Photos
    4. Modify Website to Link to Photos&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-1---login-and-create-an-s3-bucket&quot;&gt;Step 1 - Login and Create an S3 Bucket&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don’t have an AWS account, its pretty easy to create one. Just go to &lt;a href=&quot;https://aws.amazon.com/&quot;&gt;https://aws.amazon.com/&lt;/a&gt;, click “Create an AWS Account” and follow the instructions. You will have to enter credit card information to cover any costs that you incur with any of the resources you use. If you’re concerned you can look at AWS’s pricing information for more on this. I havent been charged yet and its been a couple months but I’m only using one S3 Bucket with a total of less than 40 MB. After you’ve created your account, or if you already have one, log in and get to the AWS Console.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From there, under AWS services, you can search in the box for “S3” and click the link. Alternatively you can find and click the link under &amp;gt; All Services &amp;gt; Storage &amp;gt; S3. From there it should be pretty easy to find the button with the label “Create Bucket”. Once clicked the “Create bucket” dialogue will appear. Choose a good name for the bucket, AWS has some good information on this if you click the little (i) icon next to “Bucket name” in this dialogue. I named mine luisgarcia.me-background-images for reference. You’ll also need to pick a region for it, this is worth looking into if your new to AWS but for now just pick the region closest to you. Once those two things are filled out, we’ll just accept the default settings on all the other pages, so keep clicking next until you’ve created your bucket. Now we can start configuring it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-2---configure-the-s3-bucket&quot;&gt;Step 2 - Configure The S3 Bucket&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you have the bucket go ahead and click it! This will take you to the bucket overview where you have a lot of control over your bucket. Right now, lets skip the “Overview” tab, it deals a lot with whats inside the bucket. While thats very important, I usually like to save it until the bucket is configured that way I don’t expose any sensitive data accidentally and I can remove the bucket easily if things change. A lot of the settings and confguration values we are about to change could have been chaged from the bucket creation dialog. I think its probably more important to configure a bucket once its already created though. In a bucket’s lifetime it can only be created once but its configuration could be changed any time you want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll go ahead and click the ‘Properties’ tab next. Once you’re in there, click ‘Static website hosting’ accept the defaults and click save. Similar to our Github pages, we can use buckets for static website hosting. For our purposes though, since we just want image hosting we’ll use this functionality too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After that click the ‘Permissions’ tab. This is where we’ll allow read access to our bucket. Its pretty important to get this right, so if you’re not comfortable read up a bit more on AWS S3 bucket permissions. In the permissions tab, click the “Bucket Policy” button which will open the Bucket policy editor. This is where you can copy and paste the following JSON. Be sure to change &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;bucketname&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; to the name of your bucket.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;{
    &quot;Version&quot;: &quot;2012-10-17&quot;,
    &quot;Statement&quot;: [
        {
            &quot;Sid&quot;: &quot;AllowPublicRead&quot;,
            &quot;Effect&quot;: &quot;Allow&quot;,
            &quot;Principal&quot;: {
                &quot;AWS&quot;: &quot;*&quot;
            },
            &quot;Action&quot;: &quot;s3:GetObject&quot;,
            &quot;Resource&quot;: &quot;arn:aws:s3:::&amp;lt;bucketname&amp;gt;/*&quot;
        }
    ]
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This JSON is telling AWS to create a policy named “AllowPublicRead” that grants the “GetObject” action on this S3 bucket to all resources. This policy is applied to all objects in the bucket, designated by the resource &lt;code&gt;arn:aws:s3:::&amp;lt;bucketname&amp;gt;/*&lt;/code&gt;. If you wanted to just allow public read to a specific directory you could change this to &lt;code&gt;arn:aws:s3:::&amp;lt;bucketname&amp;gt;/specificDirectory/*&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-3---upload-photos&quot;&gt;Step 3 - Upload Photos&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an easy one, go back to the “Overview” tab, click upload, and pick the files you want in the bucket. I’m using images, but you could put anything here. Notably, since we configured it to be publicly accessible, anything you put there can be accessed publicly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-4---link-to-photos&quot;&gt;Step 4 - Link to photos.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since we configured our bucket for static website hosting earlier it should be pretty easy to link to our files, or images in my case. AWS has a pretty standard way of creating url’s from buckets. This can be changed if you want, but we’ll use the default since I already have my real website somewhere else. Anyway, our photos should be avaliable at &lt;code&gt;http://&amp;lt;bucketname&amp;gt;.s3-website.us-east-2.amazonaws.com/&amp;lt;directory&amp;gt;/&amp;lt;filename&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;, note replace &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;bucketname&amp;gt; &amp;lt;directory&amp;gt; and &amp;lt;filename&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; with your relevant values. If you’re still having trouble seeing your files, check the properties tab again and click Static website hosting. Your website url should be at the top of the box that pops up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we have these links, you can alter the HTML in your other site to link to these new images and there we have it! Image hosting with AWS!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-thoughts&quot;&gt;Final Thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like this solution for the control I get over the objects, its relatively low cost, and low complexity. If one doesn’t have an AWS account, I’m sure you could do the same on the Google Cloud Platform or with Azure, other ‘cloud’ providers. I don’t like that its not free, but its a cost I can accept. Going forward, one thing I’d like to validate is the performance of loading theses images from a different place. I generally trust in the uptime and availability of the platforms hosting Github Pages and AWS S3 but it is possible that in certain cases the loading of either the site or the images could differ. Regardless I believe in the solution and I’m happy with it. This method is how I’m loading all the images you see at the top of the page so you can evaluate the solution in real time!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 08 Mar 2020 14:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/blog/technical/AWSImageHosting</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/technical/AWSImageHosting</guid>
        
        <category>AWS</category>
        
        <category>Image</category>
        
        <category>Hosting</category>
        
        <category>Github</category>
        
        <category>Pages</category>
        
        <category>Jekyll</category>
        
        
        <category>Technical</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>How to Watermark All Your Photos</title>
        <description>
&lt;p&gt;In looking at images across the internet, an reocurring element that appears in many of them is a watermark. If you’re unfamiliar with the concept, a watermark is a small design or text added to an image. The purpose behind a watermark is to visibly mark a the image to provide the creator with proof of ownership. For instance, if I mark my photos with my name and someone else downloads the image and uses it, its clear who the photo belongs to and who the original creator is. A watermark’s effectiveness is debatable. Depending on the watermark, it can be sometimes be easily cropped off. There’s also software out there designed to explicitly remove watermarks. However, leaving a watermark on an image does offer at least some security when exposing your images to the internet. In this post, I’ll describe an easy way to add a watermark to an image, and a way to automate the process so that watermarks can be added &lt;em&gt;en masse&lt;/em&gt; to a large number of photos in a short period of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ffmpeg&quot;&gt;FFmpeg&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tool I’ll be using to help us along is &lt;a href=&quot;https://ffmpeg.org/&quot;&gt;FFmpeg&lt;/a&gt;. We’ll only be using it to manipulate our images, but its great open source tool if you want to for other things like video and audio processing. Its a very powerful and versitile tool and I highly recommend it for media processing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;other-requirements&quot;&gt;Other requirements&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to FFmpeg, you’ll need at least two images, an image that you want to apply a watermark to and the watermark image itself. When designing the watermark image some things to consider are size, color, and transparency. For my watermark image, I just chose my name set at an angle. Additionally, I made sure that the background of the watermark image was 100% transparent. The transparency should allow the watermark to be seen, but the original image can still be mostly intact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;simple-overlay&quot;&gt;Simple Overlay&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Running the following command in a shell will use FFmpeg to do a simple overlay, placing the watermark image on top of the original image&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ ffmpeg.exe -i &quot;originalImage.png&quot; -i &quot;watermarkImage.png&quot; -filter_complex &quot;[0:v][1:v] overlay=main_w-overlay_w:main_h-overlay_h&quot; &quot;outputImage.png&quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The resulting image is a combination of the original image and the watermark. We’ve accomplished our goal. Now lets go into what the command is actually doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;ffmpeg.exe
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an easy one, we’re calling the executable&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;-i &quot;originalImage.png&quot; -i &quot;watermarkImage.png&quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;these two arguments assign the paths to the original image and the watermark image to the first and second inputs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;-filter_complex &quot;[0:v][1:v] overlay=main_w-overlay_w:main_h-overlay_h&quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the argument suggests, this is a complex one to explain. “filter_complex” is an argument that describes various filters to use through FFmpeg. You can read more about it &lt;a href=&quot;https://ffmpeg.org/ffmpeg-filters.html#Description&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Lets break this specific filter down though. The first things we must do is declare the inputs to the filter. In our case we’re using our two source images. The way to declare our inputs to the filter is with the square brackets. [0:v] is stating that we should use the “zero’th” or first input, our original image, and we should use the visual portion, or “video stream” from it. [1:v] is similar, only this time we’re using the second input, the watermark image. These two images will be passed to the “overlay” filter. Finally, the last piece after the “=” symbol states that the watermark’s top left corner should be placed at the point determined by two formulas. “main_w - overlay_w” determines the “x” position, where main_w is the width of the first input and overlay_w is the width of the watermark image. The “y” position is determined in a similar way. I chose to place my image in the lower right hand corner, but by manipulating these arguments the watermark can appear anywhere on the original image. For example “overlay=0:0” will place the watermark in the top left of the original image.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&quot;outputImage.png&quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the last argument is the path to the output image. This tells FFmpeg where to write your output file. If a file already exists there, FFmpeg will ask you if you want to overwrite it. If you dont want to be prompted for this question, you can just use the “-y” flag to always overwrite and “-n” flag to never overwrite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;making-a-better-watermark&quot;&gt;Making a Better Watermark&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;transparency&quot;&gt;Transparency&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My watermark started as an opaque image, that is, originally the text in my image was not transparent. A nice feature of watermarks is their transparency, it maintains the idea of marking an image as your own while also preserving as much of the image as possible. Fortunately FFmpeg offers a way for us to do that too, we can just add another filter&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;[1:v]colorchannelmixer=aa=0.5
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This filter will take our watermark image and make it 50% transparent. Putting it all together we can use this command to generate our new image&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ ffmpeg.exe -i &quot;originalImage.png&quot; -i &quot;watermarkImage.png&quot; -filter_complex &quot;[1:v]colorchannelmixer=aa=0.5[opacity];[0:v][opacity]overlay=main_w-overlay_w:main_h-overlay_h&quot; &quot;partialTransparentWatermark.png&quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This command may look a little different than expected. Using FFmpeg’s filter_complex, we can do multiple filter operations as long as we keep track of our streams. That is, now that we’ve created an video stream that is 50% transparent, we have to pass that transparent stream onto our overlay filter. I choose to keep things straight by naming the outputs of each filter result, in this case I named the output of my transparency “[opacity]”. There are other ways to pass around streams, for more information, again you can look at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ffmpeg.org/ffmpeg-filters.html#Description&quot;&gt;filter documentation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;consistency&quot;&gt;Consistency&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far we’ve done a great job watermarking our one image. However, if we continue to use the previous command on our images a problem will emerge. The watermark will appear to grow and shrink relative to the size of the image we’re watermarking. That is, if our watermark is 100x100 and we put it on a 200x200 image, the watermark will take up the bottom right quarter of the original image. If our original image is 400x400 and we use the same 100x100 watermark, then it will take up the bottom right sixteenth of the image. One solution is to create a new watermark for every image size. That does seem to get tedious very quickly. Instead lets use FFmpeg to create a more consistent watermark across all image sizes. Unfortunately, there’s not an easy way to scale an image based on the size of another image in one command. We must detect the height and width of the original image so we can scale the watermark appropriately. Fortunately, included with FFmpeg is their ffprobe program, used to gather information about a piece of media. We’ll use it to get the size of our original image.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ ffprobe.exe -i &quot;originalImage.png&quot; 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This command will result in an output that looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;ffprobe version 4.1.3 Copyright (c) 2007-2019 the FFmpeg developers
 built with gcc 8.3.1 (GCC) 20190414
 configuration: –enable-gpl –enable-version3 –enable-sdl2 –enable-fontconfig –enable-gnutls –enable-iconv –enable-libass –enable-libbluray –enable-libfreetype –enable-libmp3lame –enable-libopencore-amrnb –enable-libopencore-amrwb –enable-libopenjpeg –enable-libopus –enable-libshine –enable-libsnappy –enable-libsoxr –enable-libtheora –enable-libtwolame –enable-libvpx –enable-libwavpack –enable-libwebp –enable-libx264 –enable-libx265 –enable-libxml2 –enable-libzimg –enable-lzma –enable-zlib –enable-gmp –enable-libvidstab –enable-libvorbis –enable-libvo-amrwbenc –enable-libmysofa –enable-libspeex –enable-libxvid –enable-libaom –enable-libmfx –enable-amf –enable-ffnvcodec –enable-cuvid –enable-d3d11va –enable-nvenc –enable-nvdec –enable-dxva2 –enable-avisynth
 libavutil      56. 22.100 / 56. 22.100
 libavcodec     58. 35.100 / 58. 35.100
 libavformat    58. 20.100 / 58. 20.100
 libavdevice    58.  5.100 / 58.  5.100
 libavfilter     7. 40.101 /  7. 40.101
 libswscale      5.  3.100 /  5.  3.100
 libswresample   3.  3.100 /  3.  3.100
 libpostproc    55.  3.100 / 55.  3.100
Input #0, image2, from ‘originalImage.jpg’:
 Duration: 00:00:00.04, start: 0.000000, bitrate: 103560 kb/s
   Stream #0:0: Video: mjpeg, yuvj444p(pc, bt470bg/unknown/unknown), 2400x953 [SAR 300:300 DAR 2400:953], 25 tbr, 25 tbn, 25 tbc&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thats a lot to take in! Fortunately, we don’t need all of it. All we need is a tiny bit at the end. The resulting outpus shows Input #0 has a video stream, Stream #0:0, and its resolution is 2400x953. As with the other commands, we can simplify this one too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ ffprobe.exe -i &quot;originalImage.png&quot; -v error -hide_banner -select_streams v:0 -show_entries stream=width,height -of default=nw=1
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This command will get straight to the point and give us our width and height of this form:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;width=2400
height=953&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bringing it all back together, we use the original width and height as a base to ensure our watermark is 25% of the size of the original image. This will result in the watermark taking up 1/16 of the original image. The original image does have a weird size though, so lets try to maintain the aspect ratio of our watermark as its applied, rather than distort the watermark image. &lt;em&gt;A quick note here, there are other strategies that could be used here to provide other definitions of “consistent watermark”. I’m choosing to preserve the aspect ratio of the watermark at the expense of the inconsistencies in the height of the watermark. Another strategy could be to apply a standard scale to the both the watermark’s height and width, that could result in a stretched look of the watermark if the aspect ratio of the two images does not match.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used ffprobe again to find out my watermark’s size is 640x480&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Width Scale  = (640/480) * 2400 * .25 = x
Height Scale = (640/480) * 953 * 0.25 = y&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Width Scale  = (2400/953) * 640 * 0.25 = 402
Height Scale = (2400/953) * 480 * 0.25 = 302&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can then use these values in our ffmpeg command&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ ffmpeg.exe -i &quot;originalImage.png&quot; -i &quot;watermarkImage.png&quot; -filter_complex &quot;[1:v]scale=402:302,colorchannelmixer=aa=0.5[opacity];[0:v][opacity]overlay=main_w-overlay_w:main_h-overlay_h&quot; &quot;scaledWatermark.png&quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;automation&quot;&gt;Automation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Watermarking a large number of images could take some time if one were to do it by hand, thats why automating this process is essential. There are many ways to automate this process, and I’ve chosen to write a bash script for speed and ease. However, these methods can easily be transferred to another technology or programming language. The important pieces to keep are the processing steps. Those steps consist of the following.
    1. Identify the resolution (width and height) of the image intended to be used as a watermark with FFprobe.exe
    2. Identify the resolution (width and height) of the image that will receive the watermark with FFprobe
    3. Calculate the scale factor to apply to the watermark
    4. Create and execute the command to ffmpeg.exe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’d like to see the bash script I put together to accomplish this for myself, you can check it out on github &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/lgarcia2/ImageWatermarking&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2020 13:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>/blog/technical/Watermark</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/technical/Watermark</guid>
        
        <category>Photography</category>
        
        <category>FFmpeg</category>
        
        
        <category>Technical</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>New Blog, Who's This</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;ive-made-a-new-blog-again&quot;&gt;I’ve made a new blog! Again!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every blog of mine starts out with a post like this. So why not continue the pattern? Yes, it is very redundant to keep making different iterations of blogs every couple years. However, I’m hoping this time its different (said everyone). All of my previous blog iterations have generally been custom solutions. That is, in order to hone and practice my developer skills, I’ve implemented various web frameworks in order to come up with a blog that works for me. The good news is that I definately gained knowledge and experience from the process. The bad news is that since they were custom solutions, it wasn’t always the easiest to contribute to my own blog. I’m hoping that by avoiding custom work and switching to an established solution, contributing and keeping up with the blog will be easier. Basically, I’m trying to make the barrier to entry easier, hoping that I’ll contribute more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;introducing-jekyll&quot;&gt;Introducing Jekyll&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I chose &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt; as my ‘established solution’. Its an application developed with Ruby that takes markdown, along with some style information, to generate a static website. The main idea being that a person could write their blog posts in markdown and use Jekyll to quickly interpret and serve the content on a website. For me, the ‘pros’ are that its easy to work with, easy to contribute to, and has a lot of support. Unfortunately, there are some ‘cons’ as well. If I’m hosting a static site, its hard to embed ‘dynamic’ behavior. A few years ago, again, to practice my developer skills, I made my own version of a url shortner like &lt;a href=&quot;https://bitly.com/&quot;&gt;bit.ly&lt;/a&gt;. Unfortunately, since this is a static site I am unable to embed and host some of my projects like that (You can read more in the Github Pages section).  With that in mind though, I can always host a project somewhere else and link to it if needed. So in the end, the restrictiveness of a static site wasn’t a very big ‘con’ to me. However, there was another major ‘pro’ in using a static site: hosting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;github-pages&quot;&gt;Github Pages&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A major feature of &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/&quot;&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt; thats come out in fairly recent history has been their Github Pages concept. In essence, if you commit static web files to a repository in Github, you can configure the repository in such a way that Github will host the static website for you. Given that Github is free (for personal use) this is a great way to host a website for free. If we go back to my running ‘pros’ and ‘cons’ list, this is a pretty good ‘pro’. It also continues the ease of contribution since all I should need is Jekyll and an internet connection to contribute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-note-on-integration&quot;&gt;A Note On Integration&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the big concepts being used in modern development is Continuous Integration/Continuous Deployment (CICD). Unfortunately, one of the things I havent quite worked out yet, is how to better improve my deployment pipeline. For example, in writing this post and pushing it live, I have to have Ruby, Jekyll, and Git installed, I have to run Jekyll against the new markdown file, and finally push the new generated site to Github. I have Git, and will continue to have Git installed on all my machines but I’m not a Ruby developer. That is, Ruby and Jekyll are definately a dependency that I don’t work with on a day to day basis. As such, my desktop is the only machine I currently have running Jekyll. This restricts me to contributing to the blog only when I’m on my desktop or when Ruby and Jekyll are installed on a machine I’m working with. This isn’t very portable so CICD is something that I’d like to improve upon going forward. That is, I’d like to be able to commit changes and have the site automatically generated and re-committed so that I only have to worry about committing to Github.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;thoughts-on-jekyll-alternatives&quot;&gt;Thoughts on Jekyll Alternatives&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In picking which static site generator I had also tried &lt;a href=&quot;https://hexo.io/&quot;&gt;Hexo&lt;/a&gt;. Instead of relying on Ruby, hexo uses a Node package. So if you’re not a fan of Ruby, or have different dependencies to manage, Hexo might be a better option for you. In my experience, it does seem more flexible. However, it also seems more verbose and a tiny bit cumbersome. I’ve spent an equally small amount of time with both Jekyll and Hexo so there are definately things I haven’t come across in both options, but either should work for getting a blog up and running quickly with Github pages. There are more static site generators than these two, but since I haven’t worked with them I won’t comment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-thoughts&quot;&gt;Final Thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m sure I’ll have more opinions as I continue writing posts and continue to work with Jekyll, but so far my experience has been great. I’ve been able to customize this site to my hearts content and have not run into anything in my way. I hope that going forward, I achieve my goal of contributing more to this blog and that Jekyll helps in that regard.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 26 Apr 2019 10:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/blog/non-technical/NewBlogWhoThis</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/non-technical/NewBlogWhoThis</guid>
        
        <category>Jekyll</category>
        
        <category>Github</category>
        
        <category>Hexo</category>
        
        <category>Integration</category>
        
        <category>Deployment</category>
        
        <category>Blog</category>
        
        
        <category>Non-Technical</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Test Technical Blog</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;technical-test&quot;&gt;Technical Test&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This is a test for the Technical Blog&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 14 Apr 2019 20:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/blog/technical/Test-Technical</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/technical/Test-Technical</guid>
        
        <category>Jekyll</category>
        
        <category>GitHub</category>
        
        
        <category>Technical</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Test Non-Technical Blog</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;non-technical-test&quot;&gt;Non-Technical Test&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This is a test for the Non-Technical Blog&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 14 Apr 2019 20:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/blog/non-technical/Test-Nontechnical</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/non-technical/Test-Nontechnical</guid>
        
        <category>Jekyll</category>
        
        <category>GitHub</category>
        
        
        <category>Non-Technical</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
