<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Luis Garcia</title>
    <description>This is the personal website of Luis Garcia. Here you can read both technical and non-technical blogs, look at some projects, and get a little more insight about what makes him tick.</description>
    <link>/</link>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Aug 2020 16:57:23 -0400</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 21 Aug 2020 16:57:23 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.1.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Motorcycle Rebuild</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;1983-honda-shadow-vt500&quot;&gt;1983 Honda Shadow vt500&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Checkout the video for the TL;DR&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/RtIxz2rLDXg&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More details below…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;covid-19-and-relocation&quot;&gt;COVID-19 and Relocation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Spring and Summer of 2020, the COVID-19 pandemic was affecting the world and my spouse and I were no exception. In order to seek some fresh air and space, we ended up spending this time in Wyoming. We were pretty comfortable in our new space but we were still a bit limited in the kinds of activities we could do so I started to look for a new project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;an-old-bike&quot;&gt;An Old Bike&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started browsing Craigslist and Facebook Marketplace for a project motorcycle and started watching YouTube videos for inspiration. I saw a couple project motorcycles that didn’t work out for various reasons, but I finally found one nearby with a valid title that looked fairly decent. A seller nearby had a 1983 Honda Shadow vt 500. Unfortunately, the description of the motorcycle wasn’t very great. The person selling it received it as a part of a trade. He didn’t know what was wrong with it other than what the previous owner had stated, “A bad motor”. This isn’t usually a good sign, but I had tons of time and the price was right. The only thing I was worried about was a cracked engine block. An issue like that would be pretty difficult and expensive to fix. My spouse and I headed to the seller’s house and inspected the bike. It was in rough shape but we couldn’t see any cracks so we took it home.
&lt;img src=&quot;https://s3.us-east-2.amazonaws.com/luisorlandogarcia.com-images/non-technical/2020-08-02-Motorcycle/InTruck.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;InTruck&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;starting-work-on-the-bike&quot;&gt;Starting Work on The Bike&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;initial-problems&quot;&gt;Initial Problems&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what exactly did “rough shape” mean? There were a number of cosmetic issues, missing trim, small rust spots, but that didn’t concern me. What did was a box full of parts that had been taken off the bike. I had to make sense of these parts while trying to address the underlying issue of “A bad motor”. First though, the easiest problem to address was the lack of battery. Thats a pretty easy one to diagnose. First I put the key in the ignition and turned it. Nothing happened. That is pretty symptomatic of a dead battery, but it could be a fuse too. It was easy to see, though, that right where a battery should be, there was none. At this point I started making a list of things I needed at the part store. I couldn’t attempt to start it, but I could check some other simple things before heading out. I checked oil and coolant levels. As far as I saw, there was no coolant and when I checked the oil dipstick it was dry, so oil and coolant went on the list as well. 
&lt;img src=&quot;https://s3.us-east-2.amazonaws.com/luisorlandogarcia.com-images/non-technical/2020-08-02-Motorcycle/IncompleteWithKiki.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;IncompleteWithKiki&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;missing-battery&quot;&gt;Missing Battery&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve worked on cars and small engines before so motorcycles didn’t seem that foreign to me. An engine is an engine right? Well, I was about to find out the first difference. After a trip to the store I came back and opened the box with the battery in it. There were two containers in it and some plastic tubing. In replacing the battery I learned my first difference. Car batteries are usually sealed. You buy it and can drop it right in the vehicle. This motorcycle battery came as two parts. There is what looks like the battery with lead in it, and a separate container with acid. You have to put the acid into the battery by yourself. I’d never done it before, but its not a difficult process. The instructions are pretty detailed and the steps are more or less: put the acid into the container. That being said, it is acid so if you are going to do this yourself, be sure to take the proper precautions. After getting the battery prepped, I borrowed a trickle charger from the neighbors and started charging it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;oil-reveals-the-problem&quot;&gt;Oil Reveals the Problem&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next problem was the oil, pretty straightforward. Remove the plug and filter and let the oil drain. Then replace the filter and put back the plug. Finally, add oil until the proper level on the dipstick is reached. So I started and by loosening the oil plug and out came a mess. A sluggish pour of what looked like sweetened condensed milk started flowing from the hole. Well, thats a problem. My mind immediately jumped to a crack in the block, what I had feared before. A crack in the engine block can lead to coolant mixing with the oil. When that happens the oil starts to look milky, exactly what my oil looked like. All that being said, these symptoms also apply to other things so it might not be a crack in the block. It could just be a bad head gasket. That being said, both problems required the engine to be mostly disassembled. This is one of the most time consuming repairs one could do to a vehicle. I had high hopes though, maybe the bike had just been sitting for a long time and moisture worked its way in and mixed with the oil. I still wanted to try to start it up to verify that it was indeed a problem and so I could identify any other problems along the way. I replaced the oil, added some coolant and after the battery charger was done, I hooked up the battery and pressed the ignition button.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The engine didn’t start, but after finding the fuel valve and turning it to the “On” position I gave it another try, and lo and behold the bike came to life! Not all was well though, it ran rough and there was smoke pouring out the exhaust. These both seemed like telling signs that I had to take it apart. I turned it off and checked the oil. Sure enough it was getting more milky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;diving-in-deeper&quot;&gt;Diving in Deeper&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;prep-work&quot;&gt;Prep Work&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, this was not going to be an easy fix. While I could try to rebuild the engine with just the knowledge in my head, I figured I could probably use some help. Haynes manuals are well-known in the car world for providing all the information one would ever need on a vehicle, so I started looking around for the equivalent in the motorcycle world. I found myself a used Clymer manual with all the information I would need. If you find yourself working on a motorcycle, these manuals are great. They describe how to do all kinds of repairs, they also give all the part specifications right down to the bolt. In addition to the manuals, I found a Honda Shadow forum at hondashadow.net/forums where tons of people with Honda Shadows collaborate and discuss Honda Shadow motorcycles. I posted there with my problem and the great people there confirmed my suspicions and decision to move forward in taking the engine apart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;taking-it-apart&quot;&gt;Taking It Apart.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Clymer Manual shows exactly how to take the engine out and get it apart. That being said, sometimes it doesn’t need to be followed precisely. The Honda Shadow forums had another manual available that showed the process in a different way. The Clymer manual had extra unnecessary steps so referencing two sources helped avoid unnecessary work. I won’t go into too much detail, the manual can be reference for that, but these are the things I had to remove in order to get the engine out. I started with the seat and fuel tank. These were easy because both were missing bolts that hold them in. There is an air tube under the tank that connects the air filter box to the carburetor that popped off right after. I disconnected the throttle and choke cables that connected to the carburetor and removed it. 
&lt;img src=&quot;https://s3.us-east-2.amazonaws.com/luisorlandogarcia.com-images/non-technical/2020-08-02-Motorcycle/IncompleteBike_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;WithoutCarb&quot; /&gt; Next, I drained and removed the radiator and hoses. I had to remove the rear tire before I could remove the exhaust. Both came off easy. After that were just small trim pieces the shift lever and the rear brake lever. Finally, I placed wood blocks under the engine, took off the sub-frame, and removed the engine mounting bolts from the engine. It took a little wiggling but it came free after a bit. &lt;img src=&quot;https://s3.us-east-2.amazonaws.com/luisorlandogarcia.com-images/non-technical/2020-08-02-Motorcycle/EngineOff.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;EngineOff&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;focusing-on-the-engine&quot;&gt;Focusing on the Engine&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the engine free, I could now move on to taking it apart and looking for any coolant leaks into the engine. Most pieces came off easily and as the manual described but I did end up rounding the 12mm socket I was using on some really stuck bolts. There was also another small hidden bolt on each cylinder head that was not described in the manual. If your cylinder heads seem stuck, be sure to check for extra bolts. &lt;img src=&quot;https://s3.us-east-2.amazonaws.com/luisorlandogarcia.com-images/non-technical/2020-08-02-Motorcycle/ValveCoverOff_7.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;ValveCoverOff_7&quot; /&gt; With the heads and cylinders off I immediately saw the problem. The good news is that it wasn’t a crack in the block, or a blown head gasket. The bad news is that it was a hole right in the middle of the rear cylinder. &lt;img src=&quot;https://s3.us-east-2.amazonaws.com/luisorlandogarcia.com-images/non-technical/2020-08-02-Motorcycle/Piston_2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;HoleInPiston2&quot; /&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;https://s3.us-east-2.amazonaws.com/luisorlandogarcia.com-images/non-technical/2020-08-02-Motorcycle/Piston_5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;HoleInPiston5&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-real-problem&quot;&gt;The Real Problem&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A hole in the cylinder isn’t a very common problem. Ultimately, it turned out it was gasoline, not coolant, that was turning the oil milky. Gasoline was entering the combustion chamber, it was not being compressed properly, and who knows if it was even igniting. It does explain the engine running rough though. It is a little odd that something like that happened. The only reasons I could think of were if a foreign object entered the combustion chamber or if it maybe got to hot and weakened the metal. These days ethanol is added to some gasoline so maybe the engine got too hot and melted a hole in the piston. This is all just speculation, without being there its hard to determine the actual cause. I could have potentially identified this issue earlier if I had a compression tester, but the outcome would have been the same. In any case, I had to take apart the engine even more to collect the metal parts of the cylinder that had broken off. I cant have metal bits flying around causing more damage. Before doing that though, I ordered a new piston, piston rings, and gaskets from Ebay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;fixing-the-issue&quot;&gt;Fixing The Issue&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;waiting-for-parts&quot;&gt;Waiting for Parts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;COVID-19 definitely interrupted a lot of the day to day infrastructure we rely on, so shipping was a little slow. In the meantime I could still identify and fix other problems with the bike. First, I removed all the small metal fragments that remained from the hole in the piston. &lt;img src=&quot;https://s3.us-east-2.amazonaws.com/luisorlandogarcia.com-images/non-technical/2020-08-02-Motorcycle/Debris.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Debris&quot; /&gt;After that I took apart, cleaned and rebuilt the carburetor. It seemed mostly clean on the inside but it was comforting to know that it wouldn’t be a problem. Not only that, but it looked a lot better on the outside after cleaning. The fuel line needed replacing too, it was pretty stiff and cracked. I also started getting into the box of parts. I mostly tried to identify where they belonged, attaching them now would get in the way when I had to put the engine back in. It was a good time to address the front brakes though, they were pretty spongy. The brake fluid was a little low, so I added more and bled the system. I also tried to sort out the electrical system a little bit, there was a mess of wires up front and in the rear. I mounted the front headlight and verified it worked. The last and most time consuming thing I did was cleaning off old gasket material. The material was stuck on pretty well so the task ended up being a bit tedious, but the old material slowly came off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;replacing-the-piston-and-engine-reassembly&quot;&gt;Replacing the Piston and Engine Reassembly&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://s3.us-east-2.amazonaws.com/luisorlandogarcia.com-images/non-technical/2020-08-02-Motorcycle/Piston_7.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Piston7&quot; /&gt;
After the packages with the piston and gaskets arrived I got to work. First, I tackled the piston. I made sure to balance the new piston with the old functioning one so that I wouldn’t throw off any engine balance. There are some good YouTube tutorials on this, but its pretty straightforward. Drill a series of small dents until the pistons weigh the same. These dents should definitely be small though, don’t drill deep and don’t drill through anything. Its best make these dents where the material is thick too. The goal is to shave off material not to put holes in things. Once that was done, removing and replacing the broken piston with the new one was easy. I just removed a retaining clip and slid the old piston off. To put on the new one, I oiled up any surfaces that touched and moved, I put on the rings, slid it on the connecting rod, and put back the retaining clip. If it weren’t for the whole engine removal and disassembly, it would have been easy! &lt;img src=&quot;https://s3.us-east-2.amazonaws.com/luisorlandogarcia.com-images/non-technical/2020-08-02-Motorcycle/Piston_8.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Piston8&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next came reassembling the engine. The book was a great help here. I replaced the gaskets, assembled the parts, and torqued everything to specification. I did stumble a little bit when it came to the timing chain though. I set the camshaft, timing, and lifters easily on the front cylinder but the when it came to the rear cylinder, things just wouldn’t seat right. It seemed like the chain was too small or under too much tension and I couldn’t fit it onto the camshaft. Setting the timing correctly was out of the question. I had to disassemble almost the whole rear cylinder again to figure out the problem. It turned out to just be a kink in the chain that was a bit stuck so I made sure to lubricate the chain well. Other than that, reassembly went by the book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mounting-the-engine&quot;&gt;Mounting the Engine&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that the it was back together, I wanted nothing more than to start the engine to see if I had corrected the problem. Unfortunately, I lacked the tools and equipment to test the engine by itself so I had to reassemble the whole motorcycle to test it. With the disassembly process still fresh in my mind, and with the book by my side, this went much faster. First, I had to fit it back in the frame. Mounting and un-mounting the engine from the frame were probably the hardest parts. There wasn’t an easy way for me to lift and adjust the engine. I was working with wood boards and a floor jack so getting it in just the right spot was a little difficult. Getting help from my spouse made the process go easier, but doing this with three people might be even better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From there it was just disassembly in reverse. I put on the radiator and connected the hoses. The driveshaft (not a chain like most motorcycles) was a little difficult to line up and put on. Putting on the exhaust was simple but took some muscle and it was a dirty job. There were a load of electrical connections that needed to be made but I focused mainly on the ones just related to the engine. I tried not to put everything back, since I just needed to test if the engine ran, so I left a lot of things off for now. Some pieces like the clutch lever and gearshift weren’t essential but would also be good to test worked. I hooked up the fuel system and air-box by the book. I wanted to make sure that if I did run into problems, those two systems wouldn’t be variables. I finally mounted the fuel tank and was ready to start it up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ignition! Well, not quite at first. The engine needs to be in neutral to start, so I had to shift it a little. The fuel petcock was also in the off position so no fuel was flowing, I forgot again. Finally, the engine kill switch was in the off position. After that and after a few cranks to get the carburetor primed, it started up and ran!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;more-things-to-fix&quot;&gt;More Things to fix&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the engine sorted out, I could now pay attention to all of the other problems. Off the top of my head were a couple things. The exhaust was smokey, the engine sounded ‘click-y’, the clutch and shifting felt odd, all of the unmounted parts needed mounting, The junction box looked horrible, there were no turn signals, and a good clean was in order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started with the engine and did a lot of reading in the manual. Incorrect valve clearances seemed to explain both of the engine problems. The problem was that I remember setting them correctly when I assembled the engine in the first place. After verifying the clearances again, I noticed my problem. I set the clearances to 1mm when it should have been 0.1mm. Luckily, I didn’t need to take apart the engine for that. Its a bit tight, but there are some convenient valve covers that can be taken off to perform the necessary adjustment. That solved the clicking problem, but the exhaust was still smokey. I’d address the smokey exhaust later the cause and fix seemed easy enough for future me to solve. I’m in a high altitude area so I figured the problem could be related to the air fuel mix. Another thought was that the fuel could be bad. I had only used the fuel that came with the bike and I did not know its history. Whoops!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The clutch problem was next. I started with the simplest idea, adjusting the cable. After fiddling with a couple different adjustments, it didn’t seem to help. I figured something must have gone wrong in installation. More reading I guess. I read through the clutch portion of the manual and prepared myself to tackle the engine again. Luckily, I didn’t have to remove the engine to address the clutch, but I did have to remove a lot of those parts again. The exhaust, radiator, and sub-frame had to come off, but other than that it wasn’t too bad. Maybe I was saying that because I’d already done it once. After the sub-frame came off I drained the oil and removed the clutch cover and saw my problem. The clutch is held in place by a spring plate with four bolts going through it. Although I remember torquing it to spec, it must not have been enough because one of the bolts was more loose than the rest. &lt;img src=&quot;https://s3.us-east-2.amazonaws.com/luisorlandogarcia.com-images/non-technical/2020-08-02-Motorcycle/Clutch_2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Clutch2&quot; /&gt;This was the issue for sure. So I made sure to follow the manual to the letter and I torqued the bolts in a star pattern in three sequences. I also made sure to reference pictures and tutorials online so that I was sure everything went well this time. My guess is that since these bolts are on springs, I tightened one slightly more than another out of sequence and the loose one was more free to move. Regardless, after I reassembled everything, this solved the clutch problem and it felt great after an adjustment. I’m still not great at shifting motorcycles, but at least I know that’s a problem with me not the bike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only things left were cosmetic! I put everything on that I needed to ride safely around the block and took it for a spin. It was great to finally enjoy the fruits of my labor, even just for a bit. There was still more to to fix though. Around this time we also relocated from one corner of the state to another. I packed up the bike and its parts and we headed out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;simpler-problems&quot;&gt;Simpler Problems&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-new-problem-appears&quot;&gt;A New Problem Appears&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We ended up at my parents house for a visit. My parents and I had talked about the bike a lot on the phone and they were curious about it. Once we got it unpacked we started it up and took a few spins around the block. It was a fun time, but it pretty quickly showed another problem, a cooling problem. The engine overheated at the end of our journey and ended up spitting some coolant out the overflow. Well, add that problem to the pile. On a positive note, at my parents house I had a lot more tools and equipment to work with. My Dad’s worked on cars before too so bouncing ideas off him was a great help. After some diagnosis, we thought it was the coolant temperature sensor not sending the ‘turn on’ signal to the cooling fan. So I ordered that sensor in addition to some new turn signals, a fender, a horn, and a new junction box. The old junction box worked fine, but it was missing a cover and was a bit sketchy looking. It might have even been a safety hazard to touch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-easy-fixes&quot;&gt;The Easy Fixes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fender was easy, just putting it where it was supposed to go and finding some new bolts. The horn was also easy. I had to fabricate a bracket since it wasn’t the stock horn, but it fit fine and wired up easily. The junction box was simple but a bit time consuming. I had to take off all the electric plugs and plug them back in to the correct spot on the new box. The plugs were stiff so I had to get a little creative but the process was not complicated. &lt;img src=&quot;https://s3.us-east-2.amazonaws.com/luisorlandogarcia.com-images/non-technical/2020-08-02-Motorcycle/JunctionBox_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;JunctionBox1&quot; /&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;https://s3.us-east-2.amazonaws.com/luisorlandogarcia.com-images/non-technical/2020-08-02-Motorcycle/JunctionBox_2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;JunctionBox2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also wanted to fix the smokey exhaust. I figured it would be best to start with the carburetor. I referenced the manual more, watched some YouTube videos, and finally decided to take another stab at it. At the end of the day, I used what the manual suggested for high altitude as a baseline, but fiddled a little more with the carburetor settings in order to get it right. I still might play with it again someday because the air fuel mixture still seems a little lean. However, problem solved! The smokey exhaust is gone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;electrical-woes&quot;&gt;Electrical Woes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The turn signals arrived, and I knew there was a problem when I opened them. They had two wires to control the light, where the single signal in my possession had three wires. I should have checked before I bought them, but I thought all turn signals were more or less the same. I read a bit online about turn signals though and these seemed like they would be fine. There wouldn’t be a constant on setting for the signals, but that seemed okay to me. Tackling the electrical was a bit difficult though. There were wires everywhere, none with connectors and none labeled. I started going through them one by one referencing the wiring diagram in the manual. There were a couple issues to fix with the brake light. The switch for the front brakes had a broken contact. Getting a new switch was going to be expensive so instead I modified and added a new contact to the existing one over a couple hours. Getting all the tiny switch pieces to line up took a lot of patience. The rear brake light switch was triggered by a spring so I had to find a suitable spring for it to function. Once I resolved both these problems it was pretty satisfying to watch that brake light turn on and off. Sometimes, its the little things that keep you going. Now, with everything labeled, the turn signals seemed easy to wire up, I just left off the wires for the constant on setting. The only unfortunate part was that the signals did not flash. They were either on or off. The relay was broken so it was off to the parts store to find another. The broken relay was a three contact relay so I got a similar three contact relay. I put it in place, hooked up the wires and nothing. &lt;img src=&quot;https://s3.us-east-2.amazonaws.com/luisorlandogarcia.com-images/non-technical/2020-08-02-Motorcycle/TurnSignalRelay.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;TurnSignalRelay&quot; /&gt; Maybe the contacts were different on this relay. I tried all the combinations, but nothing worked right. I tried rewiring the turn signals and that didn’t work either. It was by happenstance that I didn’t hook up one of the wires onto the relay and that was the trick. I’m still not sure why it was wired that way. It was frustrating to have had to go through all that but the reward was working turn signals. I made sure to label and write down everything I found. I didn’t want to go through that wiring again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cooling-mistakes-and-fixes&quot;&gt;Cooling Mistakes and Fixes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final problem was cooling. The temperature sensor came in, but getting to it was a problem. It was nestled in a place that was difficult to reach. It was attached to the thermostat housing and I could could not get a wrench in the tight space. I could get a socket in there but the sensor was too long for the shallow socket I had. Ultimately, it had to come apart enough so that a wrench could fit. &lt;img src=&quot;https://s3.us-east-2.amazonaws.com/luisorlandogarcia.com-images/non-technical/2020-08-02-Motorcycle/CoolantCap.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;CoolantCap&quot; /&gt; What seemed like a simple replacement took a couple hours unfortunately. To make things worse, that turned out not to be the problem. The sensor sends a signal to the fan switch which turns on the fan when it gets to a certain temperature. It turned out the fan switch was bad. &lt;a href=&quot;https://s3.us-east-2.amazonaws.com/luisorlandogarcia.com-images/non-technical/2020-08-02-Motorcycle/FanSwitch.jpg&quot;&gt;FanSwitch&lt;/a&gt; The good news, is that we identified the problem and knew the fix. The bad news is, its another part that needs replacing. I chose another fix though. The switch should probably be replaced at some point, but instead of replacing it, I chose to short the switch. That is, I chose to bridge the two switch contacts so that the switch was always in the ‘on’ position.  This means that the fan will remain on all the time, even when the engine is cool. It might need some time to warm up on chilly days, but it prevents the engine from overheating. I fashioned a nice little wire that could be removed when the switch is eventually replaced. Finally, the bike was finished!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;final-thoughts&quot;&gt;Final Thoughts&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve taken the bike on a lot more spins around the block. I still haven’t got my Motorcycle licence endorsement so I can’t go on longer journeys, but its been a great time! This project taught me about almost every part on a motorcycle. The only thing that didn’t need fixing were the front forks and the dials. There’s a couple things I’d still want to do at some point. I’d like to fix that cooling fan switch, probably give it a paint job, and find more trim pieces. However, I think I’d feel pretty confident looking at most other motorcycles out there now, especially with a manual in hand. I would highly recommend anyone fixing a motorcycle to get a shop manual. It helped me with everything that had to be done. It was a fun project to do while I had the time and riding it after all the hard work is one of the best feelings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://s3.us-east-2.amazonaws.com/luisorlandogarcia.com-images/non-technical/2020-08-02-Motorcycle/Complete/DSC_0783.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Complete1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://s3.us-east-2.amazonaws.com/luisorlandogarcia.com-images/non-technical/2020-08-02-Motorcycle/Complete/DSC_0784.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Complete2&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://s3.us-east-2.amazonaws.com/luisorlandogarcia.com-images/non-technical/2020-08-02-Motorcycle/Complete/DSC_0789.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Complete3&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://s3.us-east-2.amazonaws.com/luisorlandogarcia.com-images/non-technical/2020-08-02-Motorcycle/Complete/DSC_0793.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Complete4&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://s3.us-east-2.amazonaws.com/luisorlandogarcia.com-images/non-technical/2020-08-02-Motorcycle/Complete/DSC_0797.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Complete5&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://s3.us-east-2.amazonaws.com/luisorlandogarcia.com-images/non-technical/2020-08-02-Motorcycle/Complete/DSC_0817.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Complete6&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 02 Aug 2020 17:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/blog/non-technical/Motorcycle</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/non-technical/Motorcycle</guid>
        
        <category>1983</category>
        
        <category>Honda</category>
        
        <category>Shadow</category>
        
        <category>500</category>
        
        <category>Motorcycle</category>
        
        
        <category>Non-Technical</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Image Hosting with AWS</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;new-website-new-problems&quot;&gt;New Website, New Problems&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m hosting this latest version of my website using Jekyll in combination with Github Pages. If you want to know more about that process you can read my post on that &lt;a href=&quot;https://luisgarcia.me/blog/non-technical/NewBlogWhoThis&quot;&gt;here.&lt;/a&gt; Its been great! I’ve still not been contributing as much as I’d like, but I am contributing more! Along with new content, I’m also able to create and deploy site design changes with just as much speed. One of those changes is how I’m hosting the images in the background at the top of the page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Originally, I only used one background image for my website, the one with four couches and a girl. I wanted was to be able to show off more of my photos, so I added the images and a little javascript to randomize when they appeared. Job well done right? Well, there are a couple problems. First, I use a reasonably decent (read: nice for 2015) camera and its images can be quite large. For that matter, media files in general, depending on quality and compression, can be quite large. Since I’m using Github to host my website, I may &lt;a href=&quot;https://help.github.com/en/github/managing-large-files/what-is-my-disk-quota&quot;&gt;run into their size restrictions&lt;/a&gt; if I store too many photos. Second, Github is generally used to store code repositories. Using it as a website hosting platform is a nice feature but those two pieces of functionality don’t alway agree on how to do things. Github and other repositories are not &lt;em&gt;generally&lt;/em&gt; the ideal place to host images. Third, every deployment with an image change can take a long time to upload to the Github server.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For my initial implementation, I was lucky enough to have the option to host my images in Github, but that needed to change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;my-first-idea&quot;&gt;My First Idea&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AWS costs money, and I didn’t want to pay. I wanted my cake and to eat it to, that is, I wanted my images to be hosted somewhere but I wanted to have strong control over those images and my IP (intellectual property). I probably could have used Imgur, Flickr, or maybe even Instagram as free public solutions to host my images. I didn’t like the inherent public nature of image hosting on the platform. For my pictures with my friends, sure they’re great. Vacation pictures, awesome! For storing my amateur photography? No way. &lt;img src=&quot;https://i.giphy.com/media/fceh5CXz9mjHa/200.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Protected GIF&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tried using a private or even public album with Google Photos, but it seems Google has gotten wise and discourages direct links to photos. It seems like some companies may have come up with ways to get around this, but most of those seemed like hack-y solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, my desire to control my images was more powerful than my desire for free solutions, but AWS S3 bucket hosting, in this case, was cheap enough for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;enter-aws&quot;&gt;Enter AWS&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m sure there are a ton of ways to configure AWS resources, store your images, and grant access to them. However, I think this method is probably the simplest and most straightforward. I chose to upload my photos to a certain directory in an S3 bucket and grant public read access to that bucket.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Breaking this down a bit, these are the steps that I needed to host images from AWS and use them on this site.
    1. Login and Create an S3 Bucket
    2. Configure the S3 Bucket
    3. Upload Photos
    4. Modify Website to Link to Photos&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-1---login-and-create-an-s3-bucket&quot;&gt;Step 1 - Login and Create an S3 Bucket&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don’t have an AWS account, its pretty easy to create one. Just go to &lt;a href=&quot;https://aws.amazon.com/&quot;&gt;https://aws.amazon.com/&lt;/a&gt;, click “Create an AWS Account” and follow the instructions. You will have to enter credit card information to cover any costs that you incur with any of the resources you use. If you’re concerned you can look at AWS’s pricing information for more on this. I havent been charged yet and its been a couple months but I’m only using one S3 Bucket with a total of less than 40 MB. After you’ve created your account, or if you already have one, log in and get to the AWS Console.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From there, under AWS services, you can search in the box for “S3” and click the link. Alternatively you can find and click the link under &amp;gt; All Services &amp;gt; Storage &amp;gt; S3. From there it should be pretty easy to find the button with the label “Create Bucket”. Once clicked the “Create bucket” dialogue will appear. Choose a good name for the bucket, AWS has some good information on this if you click the little (i) icon next to “Bucket name” in this dialogue. I named mine luisgarcia.me-background-images for reference. You’ll also need to pick a region for it, this is worth looking into if your new to AWS but for now just pick the region closest to you. Once those two things are filled out, we’ll just accept the default settings on all the other pages, so keep clicking next until you’ve created your bucket. Now we can start configuring it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-2---configure-the-s3-bucket&quot;&gt;Step 2 - Configure The S3 Bucket&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you have the bucket go ahead and click it! This will take you to the bucket overview where you have a lot of control over your bucket. Right now, lets skip the “Overview” tab, it deals a lot with whats inside the bucket. While thats very important, I usually like to save it until the bucket is configured that way I don’t expose any sensitive data accidentally and I can remove the bucket easily if things change. A lot of the settings and confguration values we are about to change could have been chaged from the bucket creation dialog. I think its probably more important to configure a bucket once its already created though. In a bucket’s lifetime it can only be created once but its configuration could be changed any time you want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll go ahead and click the ‘Properties’ tab next. Once you’re in there, click ‘Static website hosting’ accept the defaults and click save. Similar to our Github pages, we can use buckets for static website hosting. For our purposes though, since we just want image hosting we’ll use this functionality too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After that click the ‘Permissions’ tab. This is where we’ll allow read access to our bucket. Its pretty important to get this right, so if you’re not comfortable read up a bit more on AWS S3 bucket permissions. In the permissions tab, click the “Bucket Policy” button which will open the Bucket policy editor. This is where you can copy and paste the following JSON. Be sure to change &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;bucketname&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; to the name of your bucket.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;{
    &quot;Version&quot;: &quot;2012-10-17&quot;,
    &quot;Statement&quot;: [
        {
            &quot;Sid&quot;: &quot;AllowPublicRead&quot;,
            &quot;Effect&quot;: &quot;Allow&quot;,
            &quot;Principal&quot;: {
                &quot;AWS&quot;: &quot;*&quot;
            },
            &quot;Action&quot;: &quot;s3:GetObject&quot;,
            &quot;Resource&quot;: &quot;arn:aws:s3:::&amp;lt;bucketname&amp;gt;/*&quot;
        }
    ]
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This JSON is telling AWS to create a policy named “AllowPublicRead” that grants the “GetObject” action on this S3 bucket to all resources. This policy is applied to all objects in the bucket, designated by the resource &lt;code&gt;arn:aws:s3:::&amp;lt;bucketname&amp;gt;/*&lt;/code&gt;. If you wanted to just allow public read to a specific directory you could change this to &lt;code&gt;arn:aws:s3:::&amp;lt;bucketname&amp;gt;/specificDirectory/*&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-3---upload-photos&quot;&gt;Step 3 - Upload Photos&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an easy one, go back to the “Overview” tab, click upload, and pick the files you want in the bucket. I’m using images, but you could put anything here. Notably, since we configured it to be publicly accessible, anything you put there can be accessed publicly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;step-4---link-to-photos&quot;&gt;Step 4 - Link to photos.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since we configured our bucket for static website hosting earlier it should be pretty easy to link to our files, or images in my case. AWS has a pretty standard way of creating url’s from buckets. This can be changed if you want, but we’ll use the default since I already have my real website somewhere else. Anyway, our photos should be avaliable at &lt;code&gt;http://&amp;lt;bucketname&amp;gt;.s3-website.us-east-2.amazonaws.com/&amp;lt;directory&amp;gt;/&amp;lt;filename&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;, note replace &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;bucketname&amp;gt; &amp;lt;directory&amp;gt; and &amp;lt;filename&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; with your relevant values. If you’re still having trouble seeing your files, check the properties tab again and click Static website hosting. Your website url should be at the top of the box that pops up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we have these links, you can alter the HTML in your other site to link to these new images and there we have it! Image hosting with AWS!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-thoughts&quot;&gt;Final Thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like this solution for the control I get over the objects, its relatively low cost, and low complexity. If one doesn’t have an AWS account, I’m sure you could do the same on the Google Cloud Platform or with Azure, other ‘cloud’ providers. I don’t like that its not free, but its a cost I can accept. Going forward, one thing I’d like to validate is the performance of loading theses images from a different place. I generally trust in the uptime and availability of the platforms hosting Github Pages and AWS S3 but it is possible that in certain cases the loading of either the site or the images could differ. Regardless I believe in the solution and I’m happy with it. This method is how I’m loading all the images you see at the top of the page so you can evaluate the solution in real time!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 08 Mar 2020 14:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/blog/technical/AWSImageHosting</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/technical/AWSImageHosting</guid>
        
        <category>AWS</category>
        
        <category>Image</category>
        
        <category>Hosting</category>
        
        <category>Github</category>
        
        <category>Pages</category>
        
        <category>Jekyll</category>
        
        
        <category>Technical</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>How to Watermark All Your Photos</title>
        <description>
&lt;p&gt;In looking at images across the internet, an reocurring element that appears in many of them is a watermark. If you’re unfamiliar with the concept, a watermark is a small design or text added to an image. The purpose behind a watermark is to visibly mark a the image to provide the creator with proof of ownership. For instance, if I mark my photos with my name and someone else downloads the image and uses it, its clear who the photo belongs to and who the original creator is. A watermark’s effectiveness is debatable. Depending on the watermark, it can be sometimes be easily cropped off. There’s also software out there designed to explicitly remove watermarks. However, leaving a watermark on an image does offer at least some security when exposing your images to the internet. In this post, I’ll describe an easy way to add a watermark to an image, and a way to automate the process so that watermarks can be added &lt;em&gt;en masse&lt;/em&gt; to a large number of photos in a short period of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ffmpeg&quot;&gt;FFmpeg&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tool I’ll be using to help us along is &lt;a href=&quot;https://ffmpeg.org/&quot;&gt;FFmpeg&lt;/a&gt;. We’ll only be using it to manipulate our images, but its great open source tool if you want to for other things like video and audio processing. Its a very powerful and versitile tool and I highly recommend it for media processing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;other-requirements&quot;&gt;Other requirements&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to FFmpeg, you’ll need at least two images, an image that you want to apply a watermark to and the watermark image itself. When designing the watermark image some things to consider are size, color, and transparency. For my watermark image, I just chose my name set at an angle. Additionally, I made sure that the background of the watermark image was 100% transparent. The transparency should allow the watermark to be seen, but the original image can still be mostly intact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;simple-overlay&quot;&gt;Simple Overlay&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Running the following command in a shell will use FFmpeg to do a simple overlay, placing the watermark image on top of the original image&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ ffmpeg.exe -i &quot;originalImage.png&quot; -i &quot;watermarkImage.png&quot; -filter_complex &quot;[0:v][1:v] overlay=main_w-overlay_w:main_h-overlay_h&quot; &quot;outputImage.png&quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The resulting image is a combination of the original image and the watermark. We’ve accomplished our goal. Now lets go into what the command is actually doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;ffmpeg.exe
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an easy one, we’re calling the executable&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;-i &quot;originalImage.png&quot; -i &quot;watermarkImage.png&quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;these two arguments assign the paths to the original image and the watermark image to the first and second inputs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;-filter_complex &quot;[0:v][1:v] overlay=main_w-overlay_w:main_h-overlay_h&quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the argument suggests, this is a complex one to explain. “filter_complex” is an argument that describes various filters to use through FFmpeg. You can read more about it &lt;a href=&quot;https://ffmpeg.org/ffmpeg-filters.html#Description&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Lets break this specific filter down though. The first things we must do is declare the inputs to the filter. In our case we’re using our two source images. The way to declare our inputs to the filter is with the square brackets. [0:v] is stating that we should use the “zero’th” or first input, our original image, and we should use the visual portion, or “video stream” from it. [1:v] is similar, only this time we’re using the second input, the watermark image. These two images will be passed to the “overlay” filter. Finally, the last piece after the “=” symbol states that the watermark’s top left corner should be placed at the point determined by two formulas. “main_w - overlay_w” determines the “x” position, where main_w is the width of the first input and overlay_w is the width of the watermark image. The “y” position is determined in a similar way. I chose to place my image in the lower right hand corner, but by manipulating these arguments the watermark can appear anywhere on the original image. For example “overlay=0:0” will place the watermark in the top left of the original image.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&quot;outputImage.png&quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the last argument is the path to the output image. This tells FFmpeg where to write your output file. If a file already exists there, FFmpeg will ask you if you want to overwrite it. If you dont want to be prompted for this question, you can just use the “-y” flag to always overwrite and “-n” flag to never overwrite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;making-a-better-watermark&quot;&gt;Making a Better Watermark&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;transparency&quot;&gt;Transparency&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My watermark started as an opaque image, that is, originally the text in my image was not transparent. A nice feature of watermarks is their transparency, it maintains the idea of marking an image as your own while also preserving as much of the image as possible. Fortunately FFmpeg offers a way for us to do that too, we can just add another filter&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;[1:v]colorchannelmixer=aa=0.5
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This filter will take our watermark image and make it 50% transparent. Putting it all together we can use this command to generate our new image&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ ffmpeg.exe -i &quot;originalImage.png&quot; -i &quot;watermarkImage.png&quot; -filter_complex &quot;[1:v]colorchannelmixer=aa=0.5[opacity];[0:v][opacity]overlay=main_w-overlay_w:main_h-overlay_h&quot; &quot;partialTransparentWatermark.png&quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This command may look a little different than expected. Using FFmpeg’s filter_complex, we can do multiple filter operations as long as we keep track of our streams. That is, now that we’ve created an video stream that is 50% transparent, we have to pass that transparent stream onto our overlay filter. I choose to keep things straight by naming the outputs of each filter result, in this case I named the output of my transparency “[opacity]”. There are other ways to pass around streams, for more information, again you can look at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ffmpeg.org/ffmpeg-filters.html#Description&quot;&gt;filter documentation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;consistency&quot;&gt;Consistency&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far we’ve done a great job watermarking our one image. However, if we continue to use the previous command on our images a problem will emerge. The watermark will appear to grow and shrink relative to the size of the image we’re watermarking. That is, if our watermark is 100x100 and we put it on a 200x200 image, the watermark will take up the bottom right quarter of the original image. If our original image is 400x400 and we use the same 100x100 watermark, then it will take up the bottom right sixteenth of the image. One solution is to create a new watermark for every image size. That does seem to get tedious very quickly. Instead lets use FFmpeg to create a more consistent watermark across all image sizes. Unfortunately, there’s not an easy way to scale an image based on the size of another image in one command. We must detect the height and width of the original image so we can scale the watermark appropriately. Fortunately, included with FFmpeg is their ffprobe program, used to gather information about a piece of media. We’ll use it to get the size of our original image.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ ffprobe.exe -i &quot;originalImage.png&quot; 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This command will result in an output that looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;ffprobe version 4.1.3 Copyright (c) 2007-2019 the FFmpeg developers
 built with gcc 8.3.1 (GCC) 20190414
 configuration: –enable-gpl –enable-version3 –enable-sdl2 –enable-fontconfig –enable-gnutls –enable-iconv –enable-libass –enable-libbluray –enable-libfreetype –enable-libmp3lame –enable-libopencore-amrnb –enable-libopencore-amrwb –enable-libopenjpeg –enable-libopus –enable-libshine –enable-libsnappy –enable-libsoxr –enable-libtheora –enable-libtwolame –enable-libvpx –enable-libwavpack –enable-libwebp –enable-libx264 –enable-libx265 –enable-libxml2 –enable-libzimg –enable-lzma –enable-zlib –enable-gmp –enable-libvidstab –enable-libvorbis –enable-libvo-amrwbenc –enable-libmysofa –enable-libspeex –enable-libxvid –enable-libaom –enable-libmfx –enable-amf –enable-ffnvcodec –enable-cuvid –enable-d3d11va –enable-nvenc –enable-nvdec –enable-dxva2 –enable-avisynth
 libavutil      56. 22.100 / 56. 22.100
 libavcodec     58. 35.100 / 58. 35.100
 libavformat    58. 20.100 / 58. 20.100
 libavdevice    58.  5.100 / 58.  5.100
 libavfilter     7. 40.101 /  7. 40.101
 libswscale      5.  3.100 /  5.  3.100
 libswresample   3.  3.100 /  3.  3.100
 libpostproc    55.  3.100 / 55.  3.100
Input #0, image2, from ‘originalImage.jpg’:
 Duration: 00:00:00.04, start: 0.000000, bitrate: 103560 kb/s
   Stream #0:0: Video: mjpeg, yuvj444p(pc, bt470bg/unknown/unknown), 2400x953 [SAR 300:300 DAR 2400:953], 25 tbr, 25 tbn, 25 tbc&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thats a lot to take in! Fortunately, we don’t need all of it. All we need is a tiny bit at the end. The resulting outpus shows Input #0 has a video stream, Stream #0:0, and its resolution is 2400x953. As with the other commands, we can simplify this one too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ ffprobe.exe -i &quot;originalImage.png&quot; -v error -hide_banner -select_streams v:0 -show_entries stream=width,height -of default=nw=1
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This command will get straight to the point and give us our width and height of this form:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;width=2400
height=953&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bringing it all back together, we use the original width and height as a base to ensure our watermark is 25% of the size of the original image. This will result in the watermark taking up 1/16 of the original image. The original image does have a weird size though, so lets try to maintain the aspect ratio of our watermark as its applied, rather than distort the watermark image. &lt;em&gt;A quick note here, there are other strategies that could be used here to provide other definitions of “consistent watermark”. I’m choosing to preserve the aspect ratio of the watermark at the expense of the inconsistencies in the height of the watermark. Another strategy could be to apply a standard scale to the both the watermark’s height and width, that could result in a stretched look of the watermark if the aspect ratio of the two images does not match.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used ffprobe again to find out my watermark’s size is 640x480&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Width Scale  = (640/480) * 2400 * .25 = x
Height Scale = (640/480) * 953 * 0.25 = y&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Width Scale  = (2400/953) * 640 * 0.25 = 402
Height Scale = (2400/953) * 480 * 0.25 = 302&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can then use these values in our ffmpeg command&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ ffmpeg.exe -i &quot;originalImage.png&quot; -i &quot;watermarkImage.png&quot; -filter_complex &quot;[1:v]scale=402:302,colorchannelmixer=aa=0.5[opacity];[0:v][opacity]overlay=main_w-overlay_w:main_h-overlay_h&quot; &quot;scaledWatermark.png&quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;automation&quot;&gt;Automation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Watermarking a large number of images could take some time if one were to do it by hand, thats why automating this process is essential. There are many ways to automate this process, and I’ve chosen to write a bash script for speed and ease. However, these methods can easily be transferred to another technology or programming language. The important pieces to keep are the processing steps. Those steps consist of the following.
    1. Identify the resolution (width and height) of the image intended to be used as a watermark with FFprobe.exe
    2. Identify the resolution (width and height) of the image that will receive the watermark with FFprobe
    3. Calculate the scale factor to apply to the watermark
    4. Create and execute the command to ffmpeg.exe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’d like to see the bash script I put together to accomplish this for myself, you can check it out on github &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/lgarcia2/ImageWatermarking&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2020 13:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>/blog/technical/Watermark</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/technical/Watermark</guid>
        
        <category>Photography</category>
        
        <category>FFmpeg</category>
        
        
        <category>Technical</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>New Blog, Who's This</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;ive-made-a-new-blog-again&quot;&gt;I’ve made a new blog! Again!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every blog of mine starts out with a post like this. So why not continue the pattern? Yes, it is very redundant to keep making different iterations of blogs every couple years. However, I’m hoping this time its different (said everyone). All of my previous blog iterations have generally been custom solutions. That is, in order to hone and practice my developer skills, I’ve implemented various web frameworks in order to come up with a blog that works for me. The good news is that I definately gained knowledge and experience from the process. The bad news is that since they were custom solutions, it wasn’t always the easiest to contribute to my own blog. I’m hoping that by avoiding custom work and switching to an established solution, contributing and keeping up with the blog will be easier. Basically, I’m trying to make the barrier to entry easier, hoping that I’ll contribute more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;introducing-jekyll&quot;&gt;Introducing Jekyll&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I chose &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt; as my ‘established solution’. Its an application developed with Ruby that takes markdown, along with some style information, to generate a static website. The main idea being that a person could write their blog posts in markdown and use Jekyll to quickly interpret and serve the content on a website. For me, the ‘pros’ are that its easy to work with, easy to contribute to, and has a lot of support. Unfortunately, there are some ‘cons’ as well. If I’m hosting a static site, its hard to embed ‘dynamic’ behavior. A few years ago, again, to practice my developer skills, I made my own version of a url shortner like &lt;a href=&quot;https://bitly.com/&quot;&gt;bit.ly&lt;/a&gt;. Unfortunately, since this is a static site I am unable to embed and host some of my projects like that (You can read more in the Github Pages section).  With that in mind though, I can always host a project somewhere else and link to it if needed. So in the end, the restrictiveness of a static site wasn’t a very big ‘con’ to me. However, there was another major ‘pro’ in using a static site: hosting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;github-pages&quot;&gt;Github Pages&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A major feature of &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/&quot;&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt; thats come out in fairly recent history has been their Github Pages concept. In essence, if you commit static web files to a repository in Github, you can configure the repository in such a way that Github will host the static website for you. Given that Github is free (for personal use) this is a great way to host a website for free. If we go back to my running ‘pros’ and ‘cons’ list, this is a pretty good ‘pro’. It also continues the ease of contribution since all I should need is Jekyll and an internet connection to contribute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-note-on-integration&quot;&gt;A Note On Integration&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the big concepts being used in modern development is Continuous Integration/Continuous Deployment (CICD). Unfortunately, one of the things I havent quite worked out yet, is how to better improve my deployment pipeline. For example, in writing this post and pushing it live, I have to have Ruby, Jekyll, and Git installed, I have to run Jekyll against the new markdown file, and finally push the new generated site to Github. I have Git, and will continue to have Git installed on all my machines but I’m not a Ruby developer. That is, Ruby and Jekyll are definately a dependency that I don’t work with on a day to day basis. As such, my desktop is the only machine I currently have running Jekyll. This restricts me to contributing to the blog only when I’m on my desktop or when Ruby and Jekyll are installed on a machine I’m working with. This isn’t very portable so CICD is something that I’d like to improve upon going forward. That is, I’d like to be able to commit changes and have the site automatically generated and re-committed so that I only have to worry about committing to Github.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;thoughts-on-jekyll-alternatives&quot;&gt;Thoughts on Jekyll Alternatives&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In picking which static site generator I had also tried &lt;a href=&quot;https://hexo.io/&quot;&gt;Hexo&lt;/a&gt;. Instead of relying on Ruby, hexo uses a Node package. So if you’re not a fan of Ruby, or have different dependencies to manage, Hexo might be a better option for you. In my experience, it does seem more flexible. However, it also seems more verbose and a tiny bit cumbersome. I’ve spent an equally small amount of time with both Jekyll and Hexo so there are definately things I haven’t come across in both options, but either should work for getting a blog up and running quickly with Github pages. There are more static site generators than these two, but since I haven’t worked with them I won’t comment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-thoughts&quot;&gt;Final Thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m sure I’ll have more opinions as I continue writing posts and continue to work with Jekyll, but so far my experience has been great. I’ve been able to customize this site to my hearts content and have not run into anything in my way. I hope that going forward, I achieve my goal of contributing more to this blog and that Jekyll helps in that regard.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 26 Apr 2019 10:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/blog/non-technical/NewBlogWhoThis</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/non-technical/NewBlogWhoThis</guid>
        
        <category>Jekyll</category>
        
        <category>Github</category>
        
        <category>Hexo</category>
        
        <category>Integration</category>
        
        <category>Deployment</category>
        
        <category>Blog</category>
        
        
        <category>Non-Technical</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Test Technical Blog</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;technical-test&quot;&gt;Technical Test&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This is a test for the Technical Blog&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 14 Apr 2019 20:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/blog/technical/Test-Technical</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/technical/Test-Technical</guid>
        
        <category>Jekyll</category>
        
        <category>GitHub</category>
        
        
        <category>Technical</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Test Non-Technical Blog</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;non-technical-test&quot;&gt;Non-Technical Test&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This is a test for the Non-Technical Blog&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 14 Apr 2019 20:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>/blog/non-technical/Test-Nontechnical</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/non-technical/Test-Nontechnical</guid>
        
        <category>Jekyll</category>
        
        <category>GitHub</category>
        
        
        <category>Non-Technical</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
